Guide to the Frederick A. Smith, Album
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Album]
1890-1900
OSBORN D66
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.75
(4 volumes)
Autograph MSS. Collection of more than 500 letters, signatures, etc., of British statesmen, authors, scientists, etc.; Smith was employed by J. & J. Colman Ltd. at Norwich; members of the Colman family of Carrow House, Norwich, contributed significantly to this collection; many letters in these albums are addressed to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), who was M.P. for Norwich from 1871-1895, or to his son-in-law James Stuart, P.C., M.P (1843-1913); other contributors to the collection were the Rev. Mr. Barrett of Norwich, and Timothy Cole (1852-1931); the collection is strong in liberal politicians and nonconformist clergy, and many of the letters concern activities in which Smith was interested and which took place in and around Norwich.
Smith, Frederick A.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a partial inventory of the contents of Osborn d66. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Autographs -- Great Britain; Clergy -- Great Britain -- Autographs; Politicians -- Great Britain -- Autographs; Women authors; Smith, Frederick A.
- Osborn d66
  - ACLAND, SIR ARTHUR HERBERT DYKE, 1847-1926
    - 2 ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1894 (Box 3)
      Scope and Contents
      1894 Apr 10 and Nov 7
      London
      4 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      d.66/3/260
  - ALVERSTONE, RICHARD EVERARD WEBSTER, VISCOUNT, 1842-1915
    - ALS to G.S. Barrett, 1889 Jul 12 (Box 1)
      Attorney General's Chambers
      1 p.; 20 x 13 cm.
      d.66/1/3
  - ATKINS, FREDERICK ANTHONY, 1864-?
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1893 Apr 25 (Box 2)
      1 p.; 26 x 20 cm.
      d.66/2/154
  - BARRY, SIR JAMES MATTHEW, 1860-1937
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1896 Mar 8 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      Declines an offer to lecture.
      d.66/3/320
  - BATTERSEA, CYRIL FLOWER, 1ST BARON, 1843-1907
    - ALS to Mr. Barrett, [no yr] Apr 19 (Box 3)
      Athens
      d.66/3/253
  - BEECHER, EUNICE WHITE (BULLARD), 1813-1897
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1893 Mar 15 (Box 2)
      Brooklyn
      2 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Sends an autograph of Henry Ward
      Beecher (1813-1887) but explains
      that demand for his signature has
      been so high very few examples of
      his hand have been left.
      d.66/2/114
  - BENJAMIN-CONSTANT, JEAN JOSEPH, 1845-1902
    - ALS to Timothy Cole (1852-1931), [1900] Feb 13 (Box 4)
      [Paris]
      1 p.; 18 x 14 cm.
      Sends his visiting hours.
      d.66/4/382
  - BENN, SIR JOHN WILLIAMS, BART., 1850-1922
    - ALS to Mr. Bennett, 1890 Aug 11 (Box 1)
      Gives possible dates for a visit to
      Norwich.
      d.66/1/29
  - BERRY, CHARLES ALBERT, 1852-1899
    - ALS to Mr. Smith, 1893 Oct 28 (Box 2)
      Wolverhampton
      Thanks for a donation sent.
      d.66/2/133
  - BROADHURST, HENRY, 1840-1911
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1893 Dec 18 (Box 3)
      d.66/3/233
  - BRYCE, JAMES BRYCE, VISCOUNT, 1838-1922
    - ALS to [Jeremiah James] Colman (1830-1899), 1893 Aug 18 (Box 1)
      3 p.; 19 x 12 cm.
      Declines an invitation as he plans
      to close the Home Rule Book at the
      same time.
      d.66/1/27
  - BUCKINGHAM, JAMES SILK, 1786-1855
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1842 Feb (Box 1)
      1 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Asks the recipient to place his name
      on the subscription list for the
      author's new work on the "Slave
      States" of the "Free States of
      America."
      d.66/1/33
  - BURRITT, ELIHU, 1810-1879
    - page of MS, n.d. (Box 3)
      1 p.; 25 x 13 cm.
      d.66/3/236
  - BUSS, SEPTIMUS
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1893 Dec 12 (Box 3)
      2 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      Thanks for game and praises the
      progress which "liberal measures"
      are making in the House.
      d.66/3/241
  - BUTE, JOHN PATRICK CRICHTON-STUART, MARQUIS OF, 1847-1900
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1895 Mar 20 (Box 3)
      Dumfries House
      3 p.; 15 x 10 cm.
      Hopes that Stuart will be present at
      the meeting of the General Council
      at Saint Andrews in order to vote on
      medical resolutions and the bill for
      "dissolving the union".
      d.66/3/303
  - BUXTON, SYDNEY CHARLES, 1853-
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1833-1899), 1894 Apr 24 (Box 3)
      Assures him that his recommendation
      will be considered.
      d.66/3/254
  - CAMPBELL-BANNERMAN, SIR HENRY, 1836-1908
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1893 Apr 24 (Box 1)
      Promises to inquire into the matter
      requested by Stuart.
      d.66/1/4
  - CARLYLE, THOMAS, 1795-1881
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1869 Dec 9 (Box 4)
      Chelsea
      4 p.; 10 x 11 cm.
      Discusses a collection of books
      which the recipient wished to sell
      and encourages him to persevere in
      his hard times.
      d.66/4/368
  - CAVE, ALFRED, 1847-1900
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1894 Nov 25 (Box 3)
      Hackney College
      2 p.; 20 x 13 cm.
      d.66/3/277
  - CONRAD, JOSEPH, 1857-1924
    - Fragment of an unpublished MS, 1899 Feb 10 (Box 4)
      n.p.
      d.66/4/388
  - CROSS, RICHARD ASSHETON CROSS, 1ST VISCOUNT, 1823-1914
    - ALS to William Tallack (1831-1908), 1892 Jun 27 (Box 3)
      Thinks Tallack should send his
      request to the proper party himself.
      d.66/3/231
  - DODS, MARCUS, 1834-1909
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1894 Feb 23 (Box 2)
      Edinburgh
      1 p.; 15 x 10 cm.
      Declines a request to supply the
      recipient with books at a discount
      rate.
      d.66/2/141
  - DOYLE, SIR ARTHUR CONAN, 1859-1930
    - ALS to Miss Tipple, 1894 Jul 16 (Box 3)
      South Norwood
      Accepts an invitation to visit.
      d.66/3/282
  - EVERSLEY, GEORGE JOHN SHAW-LEFEVRE, BARON, 1832-1928
    - ALS to Jeremiah Jones Colman (1830-1899), 1894 Dec 7 (Box 3)
      Explains the role of the Local
      Government Board in the appointment
      of Registrars of Births and Deaths.
      d.66/3/261
  - FARNBOROUGH, SIR THOMAS ERSKINE MAY, BARON, 1815-1886
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1884 Nov 15 (Box 3)
      Reply to an inquiry.
      d.66/3/273
  - FARRAR, FREDERIC WILLIAM, 1831-1903
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, [no yr] Jan 21 (Box 2)
      2 p.; 10 x 8 cm.
      d.66/2/108
  - FOSTER, MYLES BIRKET, 1825-1899
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1894 Feb 1 (Box 3)
      Witley, Surrey
      1 p.; 10 x 9 cm.
      Thanks Smith for having inquired
      about his health.
      d.66/3/242
  - FREELING, SIR FRANCIS, BART., 1764-1836
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1817 May 8 (Box 1)
      General Post Office
      2 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      d.66/1/41
  - GILL, THOMAS HORNBLOWER
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1886 Feb 14 (Box 2)
      Lewisham
      Annexes to his allowances the use of
      certain hymns.
      d.66/2/155
  - GISSING, GEORGE ROBERT, 1857-1903
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1897 Mar 7 (Box 4)
      Epsom
      Declines Smith's request for free
      copies of his books.
      d.66/4/329
  - GLADSTONE, CATHERINE (GLYNNE), 1813-1900
    - ALS to James Stuart, [1893] Dec 31 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 19 x 12 cm.
      Invitation to dinner.
      d.66/3/228
  - GLADSTONE, HELEN, 1849-
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1893 Dec 15 (Box 3)
      2 p.; 19 x 12 cm.
      Thanks him on the part of her mother
      for the gifts he had sent.
      d.66/3/229
  - GLADSTONE, WILLIAM EWART, 1809-1898
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1878 Apr 12 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 7 x 12 cm.
      Thanks for a sermon sent to him.
      d.66/1/2
  - GLADSTONE, WILLIAM EWART, 1809-1898
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1891 Nov 7 (Box 1)
      Discusses the press.
      d.66/1/1
  - GRANVILLE, GRANVILLE LEVESON-GOWER, EARL, 1773-1846
    - ALS to the President of French Conseil d'etat, 1832 Jan 30 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 26 x 19 cm.
      Requests a letter.
      d.66/1/39
  - GREEN, SAMUEL GOSNELL, 1822-1905
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1893 Jul 12 (Box 2)
      Sends a specimen of his writing.
      d.66/2/124
  - GURNEY, JOSEPH JOHN, 1788-1847
    - Note to Seth William Stevenson (1784-1853), 1840 May 31 (Box 2)
      Norwich
      1 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Thanks him for a review.
      d.66/2/204
  - HARCOURT, SIR WILLIAM GEORGE GRANVILLE...VERNON, 1827-1904
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1894 Feb 9 (Box 1)
      Declines the Presidency of the
      Gladstone Club at Norwich.
      d.66/1/93
  - HARTE, BRET, 1836-1902
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1887 Oct 13 (Box 4)
      Brandon, Norfolk
      Declines an offer from the recipient.
      d.66/4/355
  - HAWKINS, SIR JOHN, 1532-1595
    - Signature, on a fragment, n.d. (Box 2)
      1 p.; 6 x 10 cm.
      d.66/2/209
  - HOARE, SIR SAMUEL, BART., 1841-1915
    - ALS to James W. Reeve, 1891 Oct 11 (Box 1)
      Norfolk
      Thanks him for a report of sketches.
      d.66/1/18
  - HOGARTH, WILLIAM, 1697-1764
    - AL (in 3rd person) to Mr. King, n.d. (Box 2)
      1 p.; 11 x 15 cm.
      Illustrated invitation to dinner.
      d.66/2/210
  - HOLDEN, ANGUS HOLDEN, BARON, 1833-1912
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1893 Dec 29 (Box 3)
      Bradford
      Sends with a petition which he
      requests Stuart to place "in the Bag
      behind the Speaker's Chair, after
      attaching your signature."
      d.66/3/235
  - IBSEN, HENRIK, 1828-1906
    - Calling card with autograph notations, 1897 Dec 10 (Box 4)
      Krissiania
      1 p.; 7 x 11 cm.
      d.66/4/372
  - JERROLD, DOUGLAS WILLIAM, 1803-1857
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1852 Jul 13 (Box 3)
      Declines an offer [to speak?] but
      sends the recipient to Charles John
      Huffam Dickens (1812-1870) for help.
      d.66/3/247
  - JESSOPP, AUGUSTUS, 1824-1914
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1894 Jul 15 (Box 3)
      East Denham
      Answers the recipient's queries.
      d.66/3/237
  - KENNAN, GEORGE, 1845-1924
    - ALS to William Tallack (1831-1908), 1890 Jan 16 (Box 2)
      Grand Rapids, Mich.
      2 p.; 20 x 12 cm.
      The first and last pages of a
      fourteen-page letter.
      d.66/2/186
  - KIMBERLY, JOHN WODEHOUSE, 1ST EARL OF, 1826-1902
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1894 Mar 14 (Box 1)
      d.66/1/88
  - KIPLING, RUDYARD, 1865-1936
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1893 Dec 23 (Box 2)
      Brattleboro, Vermont
      Reply to a request for publications.
  - LANG, ANDREW, 1844-1912
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1897 Feb 21 (Box 4)
      St. Andrews
      "Do you really suppose that I can
      afford better to give my books away
      to young men's associations than
      they can afford to buy them?"
      d.66/4/328
  - LEGGE, AUGUSTUS, BP. OF LICHFIELD, 1839-1913
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1893 Jan 26 (Box 3)
      Lichfield
      Thanks for the papers and volume
      sent to him.
      d.66/3/238
  - LOPES, SIR MANASSEH MASSEH, 1ST BART., 1755-1831
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1828 Feb 8 (Box 1)
      Maristow House
      1 p.; 28 x 19 cm.
      Returns a parcel which he mistakenly
      took for his.
      d.66/1/40
  - LYTTON, EDWARD LYTTON BULWER-LYTTON, 1ST BARON, 1803-1873
    - ALS to Messrs. Chapman and Hall, 1850 Jan 19 (Box 3)
      Nice
      1 p.; 11 x 12 cm.
      Written on the flap of an envelope.
      d.66/3/313
  - MACAULAY, THOMAS BABINGTON MACAULAY, BARON, 1800-1859
    - ALS to Westley and Co., 1859 Jun 21 (Box 2)
      Kensington
      Requests that some of his books be
      bound.
      d.66/2/150
  - MAPLE, SIR JOHN BLUNDELL, 1845-1903
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1895 Feb 16 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      Sends a copy of his "Cheap Trains"
      bill.
      d.66/3/310
  - MARTINEAU, JAMES, 1805-1900
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1893 Mar 9 (Box 2)
      Gordon Square
      2 p.; 15 x 10 cm.
      Reply to a request for books.
      d.66/2/161
  - MIALL, CHARLES S.
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1877 Aug 1 (Box 4)
      1 p.; 18 x 13 cm.
      Thanks him for his money and informs
      him of his present activities.
      d.66/4/399
  - MIALL, EDWARD, 1809-1881
    - ALS to Skeats, 1862 Aug 22 (Box 2)
      Llandudno
      d.66/2/165
  - MONKSWELL, ROBERT COLLIER, 2ND BARON, 1845-1909
    - ALS to William Tallack (1831-1908), 1892 Feb 18 (Box 3)
      Thanks him for having sent a copy of
      "Periological and Prevention"
      principles.
  - MUNDELLA, ANTHONY JOHN, 1825-1897
    - ALS to William Tallack, 1831-1908, 1892 Oct 10 (Box 1)
      Answers a letter about the
      jurisdiction of the Board of Trade
      vis-a-vis the Building Societies.
      d.66/1/87
  - MURCHISON, SIR RODERICK IMPEY, 1792-1871
    - ALS to the Editor of the Recorder, 1865 Aug 24 (Box 2)
      Keir Dunblane, N.B.
      Writes to amend a letter he had
      written to the Times concerning Lake
      Albert in Africa.
      d.66/2/202
  - NEWMAN, JOHN HENRY, CARDINAL, 1801-1890
    - AL to [G.S. Barrett], 1856 Feb 13 (Box 2)
      1 p.; 12 x 9 cm.
      Authorizes the Editor of the
      Congregational to insert certain
      hymns.
      d.66/2/107
  - NOEL, RODEN BERKELEY WRIOTHESLEY, 1834-1894
    - ALS to G. Barrett, 1882 Aug 21 (Box 2)
      Cromer
      Invitation to dine.
      d.66/2/156
  - NORFOLK, HENRY FITZALAN-HOWARD, 15TH DUKE OF, 1847-1917
    - ALS to Caroline Colman, Mrs. Jeremiah James Colman, 1894 Feb 28 (Box 3)
      d.66/3/232
  - NORTHAMPTON, WILLIAM GEORGE SPENCER, MARQUIS OF, 1851-1913
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1893 Jun 2 (Box 3)
      3 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      Expresses his reservations
      concerning Stuart's sponsoring of a
      Royal Commission inquiry into the
      Post Office.
  - OLDROYD, SIR MARK, 1843-1927
    - ALS to Caroline Colman (Mrs. J.J. Colman), 1893 Dec 5 (Box 1)
      Thanks Mrs. Colman for her concern
      about the "missing Parliamentary
      Papers."
      d.66/1/35
  - PAGET, FRANCIS, BP. OF OXFORD, 1851-1911
    - ALS to Mrs. Barrett, 1890 Aug 2 (Box 2)
      Oxford
      Invitation to tea.
      d.66/2/109
  - PARKER, JOSEPH, 1830-1902
    - TLS to Dr. Barrett, 1894 Apr 10 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 29 x 22 cm.
      Has already committed his votes to
      another; is readying to sit for a
      portrait.
      d.66/3/248
  - PEMBERTON, SIR MAX, 1863-
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1894 Feb 21 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 27 x 20 cm.
      Declines to give Smith free books but
      sends him to an establishment which
      will provide him with books at half
      price.
      d.66/3/239
  - PHILLPOTTS, EDEN, 1862-
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1896 Feb 19 (Box 3)
      Declines request for free copies of
      books but supplies the recipient
      with the publishers names so that he
      may approach them directly.
      d.66/3/281
  - PICTON, JAMES ALLANSON, 1832-1910
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1894 Sep 16 (Box 3)
      Caerlyr by Conway
      Asks for help from the St. Anne's
      Society.
      d.66/3/272
  - PUNSHON, WILLIAM MORLEY. 1824-1881
    - ALS to Thomas Mapplebeck, 1880 Nov 24 (Box 2)
      Manchester
      d.66/2/136
  - RAFFLES, THOMAS, 1788-1863
    - ALS to W.J. Barrett, 1855 Dec 6 (Box 2)
      Liverpool
      d.66/2/117
  - REED, EDWARD TENNYSON, 1860-
    - ALS to Frederick A. Smith, 1893 Dec 5 (Box 2)
      Provides the collector with a sample
      of his writing and has sketched in
      watercolors a hunchback elf in the
      top left corner of his stationary.
      d.66/2/215
  - RICHARD, HENRY, 1812-1888
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1874 Oct 22 (Box 4)
      Dolagren
      Declines an invitation.
      d.66/4/376
  - ROSEBERY, ARCHIBALD PHILIP PRIMROSE, EARL OF, 1847-1929
    - TLS to [Jeremiah James] Colman (1830-1899), 1894 Feb 2 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Declines the offer of the Presidency
      of the Gladstone Liberal Club at
      d.66/3/227
  - SERGEANT, EMILY FRANCES ADELINE, 1851-1904
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1896 Feb 21 (Box 3)
      Alessio, Italy
      Informs the recipient that she will
      not be able to supply him with free
      copies of her books.
      d.66/3/288
  - SHUTTLEWORTH, UGHTRED KAY-SHUTTLEWORTH, BARON, 1844-1939
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1893 Apr 26 (Box 1)
      d.66/1/5
  - SINCLAIR, WILLIAM MACDONALD, 1850-?
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1893 Sep 4 (Box 2)
      d.66/2/131
  - SMITH, ELIZABETH THOMASINA (MEADE), 1854-1914
    - TLS to Frederick A. Smith, 1896 Feb 14 (Box 3)
      West Dulwich
      1 p.; 17 x 20 cm.
      Promises to send copies of one or
      two books written by her under her
      pseudonym and of which she has
      duplicates.
      d.66/3/283
  - SPENCER, JOHN POYNTZ SPENCER, 5TH EARL, 1835-1910
    - ALS to Timothy Cole (1852-1931), 1897 Nov 7 (Box 4)
      Althorp
      Has received the proofs of the
      engraving of the portrait of the
      Duchess of Devonshire by Sir Joshua
      Reynolds (1723-1792).
      d.66/4/390
  - STEAD, WILLIAM THOMAS, 1849-1912
    - TLS to F.C. Bennett, 1890 Aug 19 (Box 2)
      1 p.; 25 x 20 xm.
      Gives Bennett his opinion on having
      Stepniak (pseud.; Sergyei
      Mikhailovich Kravchinskii, 1825-1895)
      speak on the platform.
      d.66/2/177
  - THAYER, WILLIAM MAKEPEACE, 1820-1898
    - ALS to Hodder & Stoughton, 1892 Nov 23 (Box 2)
      Franklin, Massachussetts
      Informs them of his printer's delay
      in readying his manuscript.
      d.66/2/170
  - TREVELYAN, SIR CHARLES PHILIPS, 3RD BART., 1870-1958
    - ALS to James Stuart, 1894 Jan 10 (Box 3)
      Grosvenor Crescent
      Discusses the number of Tories
      versus Liberals.
      d.66/3/234
  - TREVELYAN, SIR GEORGE OTTO, 1838-1928
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1896 Apr 23 (Box 3)
      Thanks Colman for having sent on a
      news concerning a particular case.
  - WARWICK, HENRY RICHARD GREVILLE, 3RD EARL OF, 1779-1853
    - ALS to John William Ponsonby, 4th earl of Bessborough (1781-1847), 1834 Aug 17 (Box 1)
      Warwick Castle
      3 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      d.66/1/42
  - WELLES, WELHAM
    - ALS to Jeremiah James Colman (1830-1899), 1894 Jan 29 (Box 1)
      Thanks Colman for a recent gift.
      d.66/1/92
  - WHISHAW, FREDERICK JAMES, 1854-1934
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1896 Feb 19 (Box 3)
      Upper Norwood
      Sends the inquirer to the publishers
      for free copies of his books.
      d.66/3/280